Finding aid for Women in Science and Engineering Program (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library
Women in Science and Engineering Program (University of Michigan) records 1888-1928 1888-1889
1974-1996
2004-2019
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Women in Science and Engineering Program.
032 Bimu 2
3.0 linear feet
79.7 GB (online)
1 archived websites
Established in 1980 as part of the Center for Continuing Education of Women (now CEW+), the Women in Science and Engineering Program (WISE) has sought to increase the number of women who major in and seek advanced degrees in mathematics, science and technical fields. WISE has offered internships, resource guides, programming, and the Warner-Lambert lecture series towards this goal. In addition to supporting women at the collegiate level, WISE offers a variety of K-12 programs for students of any gender identity, although they are primarily aimed at women and girls. Records include correspondence; physical and digital materials related to programming efforts, including the Warner-Lambert lecture series and Girls in Science and Engineering summer camp; funding proposals; research papers and talks by WISE staff members; and clippings and documents related to the establishment of WISE. Planning files for the Girls and Science and Technology (GASAT) IV Conference 1987 are included as well as digital transcripts and recordings from an oral history project that sought to preserve the history of University of Michigan alumnae in the sciences and engineering.
The record group (donor no. 9222 ) was received from the unit in June 2002. Additional accessions were received in March 2018 and January 2020.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
Restrictions apply; see item listing for details.
Access to select audiovisual content in the Programming series is restricted to the reading room of the Bentley Historical Library.
In 1980, the University of Michigan established the Women in Science Program as part of the Center for Continuing Education of Women (now Center for Education of Women+, or CEW+), with Dr. Barbara Sloat as the program's first director. The program has sought over the years to increase the number of women and girls who major and seek advanced degrees in mathematics, science, and technical fields, particularly via programming efforts which are open to students of any gender identity. In 1994, the program changed its name to Women in Science and Engineering (WISE) to reflect support for women in science as well as engineering. While WISE had always supported women in engineering (made apparent by many early programming endeavors), the common interpretation of "science" at the time excluded engineering. The name change was designed to bridge the gap in terminology.
In its initial years, the program was funded by joint contributions from the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts; the College of Engineering; the Medical School; the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies; and the Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs. In the two decades since its inception, WISE applied for and received considerable funds from outside sources while continuing to work under the auspices of CEW. Today, WISE is an independent program supported by the College of Engineering; the College of Literature, Sciences and Arts; and the Office of the Provost. The director of WISE reports to the Vice Provost for Engaged Learning.
WISE has supported undergraduate and graduate women through a variety of programs, including workshops, roundtable discussions, "tray lunches," and conferences. Prominent in the early years was the Women in Science Workshop, offered each fall for incoming women in both the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts and College of Engineering who were interested in science and mathematics-related majors and careers. The workshop afforded students the opportunity to meet female scientists and obtain information about science and engineering programs at the university.
Of particular significance is the Warner-Lambert Lecture Series, begun in 1981 with a gift of $15,000. This gift from the Warner-Lambert Foundation allowed WISE to co-sponsor, with departments across campus, lectures by visiting women scientists as well as sponsor university-wide lectures by outstanding women scientists. Faculty members across campus were invited to submit nominations for speakers, which were then reviewed by a faculty advisory committee. Well over 100 women scientists were brought to campus as a direct result of this program.
In addition to supporting internships in the sciences for undergraduate women in cooperation with the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, WISE and University Housing established the Women in Science and Engineering Residence Program (WISE RP) in 1993. Designed for first- and second-year students who are majoring in science, technology, engineering, mathematics, pre-health, nursing or kinesiology, WISE RP supports WISE's mission by developing a community learners via study groups, peer mentoring, coursework, and events. WISE has also provided counseling and advising services, as well as resource guides, for students.
WISE has also sought from early on to encourage girls and minorities in K-12 schools to take an interest in science. With the support of a Sigma Xi pre-college education grant, WISE sponsored two "Science Day on Campus" events in 1988 and brought local high school girls to campus to get career information and tours of the laboratories of female scientists. Among the other pre-college programs supported by WISE were Summerscience for Girls and high school internships. Summerscience, first held in 1989 with funding from the Young Scholars program of the National Science Foundation, brought nearly 50 girls to campus to do hands-on projects in the sciences. Additional NASA funding in the second year allowed the program to expand to 75 students. In 1992, a joint project by Warner-Lambert/Parke-Davis and the Women in Science Program received federal funding from the National Institute of Health Science Education Award Program. The joint project -- "Science for Life: A Summer Program for High School Women" -- placed twenty high school women between their junior and senior years in research laboratories for a six-week period.
Other K-12 programs that WISE has offered have included the Girls in Science and Engineering (GISE) Camp, a summer camp that focused on STEM topics (e.g. chemistry, engineering, robotics, human genetics, and physics) and the Southeast Michigan Science Fair, which is sponsored by the University of Michigan and Washtenaw Community College. WISE has also been involved in the FIRST LEGO League, an international program designed to introduce pre-college students to STEM topics via a robotics competition. WISE offered a variety of K-12 summer programs in 2020, including the GISE Camp, Python Bootcamp, Girls in Music and Technology (GiMaT) summer commuter program, and Electrify Tech Camp.
WISE staff have also conducted a number of scientific research projects on campus and made themselves available to give papers and talks at local, state, and national events and conferences. The program has also been involved in international efforts encouraging girls in scientific fields, as exemplified by WISE staff members hosting the 1987 Girls and Science and Technology (GASAT) IV conference in Ann Arbor. Founded in 1979 by researchers in Northern Europe who were concerned with the participation of girls and women in scientific fields, GASAT held international conferences bringing individuals around the world together to discuss their work on issues relating to girls and science.
WISE, along with its programs and staff, has received several awards over the years, including a National Science Foundation Recognition Award for the Integration of Research and Education (1997), Presidential Award for Excellence in Science, Mathematics, and Engineering Mentoring (2000), and Maria Mitchell Women in Science Award (presented to WISE's second Director, Cinda-Sue Davis, in 2000).
After receiving a grant from the Alumnae Council Birthday Greeting Committee in 2004, the Women in Science and Engineering Program, under the direction of Dr. Cinda-Sue Davis, initiated an oral history project to collect and preserve the oral histories of University of Michigan alumnae in the sciences and engineering. Interview subjects were selected based on their integrity, social consciousness, and citizenship, and not simply on their technical ability or accomplishments. Furthermore, the oral histories focus on the whole interview subject, not simply her experience in a technological field. Interview subjects spoke candidly about their hopes, fears, regrets, and triumphs in all aspects of their lives: education, career, marriage, family, and retirement. They have discussed at length how their treatment and experiences led to, sidetracked, or thwarted their attempts as scientists, engineers, or technicians. The Women's History in Michigan Science and Engineering Oral History Project completed its interviews in 2007. The project resulted in a website (which provided this description) as well as audio recordings and transcripts.
Directors of the Women in Science and Engineering Program
1980-1984 Barbara Sloat
1984-2019 Cinda-Sue Davis
2019- Melissa Gross
The WISE records (3.0 linear feet and digital files (online)) reflect the changing approaches that WISE took to encourage and support women in the sciences and engineering, as well as the changing organizational structure of the program. Specific formats include correspondence, digital photographs and videos, grant applications and program proposals, oral histories, research studies and talks, publications, reports, web archives, and background material on women and sciences at the University of Michigan. Prominently represented in the collection are WISE's various programming efforts as well as the Women's History in Michigan Science and Engineering Oral History Project.
Arranged in 7 series: 1. Administrative. 2. Outreach. 3. Programming. 4. Research. 5. Girls and Science and Technology (GASAT) IV. 6. Women's History in Michigan Science and Engineering Oral History Project 7. Archived Website.
Engineering -- Study and teaching.; Human genetics -- Study and teaching.; Robotics -- Study and teaching.; Science -- Study and teaching.; Women college students -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Women engineers.; Women in engineering.; Women in science.; Women scientists.; Digital file formats.; Oral histories (document genres).; Photographs.; Web sites.; Ajzenberg-Selove, Fay, 1926-; Buckley, Paulita.; Carter, Barbara (Barbara Quinn); Connable, Tenho.; FIRST Robotics Competition.; Frank, Margaret (Margaret Barson); Holter, Francis.; Kelly, Marilee.; Natvig, Anne.; Patterson, Dorothy (Dorothy Lewis); Pilchard, Patricia.; Shumway, Sally.; Sloat, Barbara F.; University of Michigan -- Camps.; University of Michigan. Women in Science and Engineering Program.; London, Ted, 1963-
- Administrative, 1977-1996; 1.25 linear feet
  The Administrative series (1.25 linear feet) is an alphabetically arranged sequence providing insight into the day-to-day operation and structure of the WISE program. Records describe the history and creation of the WISE program, and also include correspondence and documents relating to early funding arrangements. Also of note are position papers and listings of program activities and accomplishments that describe the program's early endeavors and justify its purpose and existence.
  - Background/History
    - Advisory Committee, 1980; 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Funding Arrangements, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Grade Point Average Comparisons, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Internship Committee, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Minority Engineering Program Office Report, July 1979 (Box 1)
    - News Clippings (Box 1)
    - Newsletters, 1981-1982; 1984; 1986 (Box 1)
    - Position Papers, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
    - Program Activities and Accomplishments, 1980-1984; 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Science and Technology Workforce, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Women Faculty Instructional Rankings, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Women in Academic Science Discussion Group, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Women in Science and Technology Equal Opportunity Act, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Women in Science Brochures, ca., 1980-1990 (Box 1)
    - Women's Caucus Efforts, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
  - Funding
    - Development Office Contact, 1981; 1983 (Box 2)
    - IBM Proposal for Internships, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    - Shell Funds for Women's Careers, 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Solicitations, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - King/Chavez/Parks College Day Program, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Science Development Council, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
- Outreach, 1980-1992
  The Outreach series (0.25 linear feet) includes a number of papers and talks given by WISE staff at various conferences, workshops, and educational group meetings. These records provide snapshots of the WISE program as well as more personal reflections on the program's development and purpose, while at the same time situating it in national context. The series also contains various directories and listings created by WISE to aid students in locating resources in the sciences.
  - High School Outreach Program, 1982-1985 (Box 2)
  - Papers
    - "Determinants of Choice of Undergraduate Concentrations in the Sciences, Mathematics, and Engineering at the University of Michigan," 1989. (Box 2)
    - "Women in Science: A University Program of Intervention, Outreach, and Research." Presented at the Second International Interdisciplinary Congress on Women, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Resources
    - Bibliography: Holdings in the CEW Library, 1981; 1992 (Box 2)
    - Departmental Resources Persons Listing, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Resource Directory of Michigan Women in the Sciences, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Resource List of National Organizations of and for Women in Science, 1980-1981; 1991 (Box 2)
    - Resource Locator: Careers in the Health Sciences, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Women and Science Acquisitions, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Science By Mail Volunteer Program, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Talks/Addresses
    - Michigan Science Teachers Association, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Science Workshop for Secondary Teachers, 1987 (Box 2)
    - St. Cloud State University Conference on Women in Mathematics, 1989 (Box 2)
    - State Superintendent's Special Committee on Minorities, Females and Handicappers, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Washtenaw Intermediate School District, 1990 (Box 2)
- Programming, 1974-1975; 1980-1996; 2004-2011; 2017-2018
  The Programming series (1.0 linear feet and digital files (online)) provides the researcher with the greatest insight into the main work of WISE -- a vast array of programming efforts -- and its changing strategies and priorities.
  The series includes digital photographs and videos from various WISE programs, particularly its FIRST LEGO League teams and Girls in Science and Engineering (GISE) Camp; documentation related to the 2017 "Hidden Figures: When the Computer Wore a Skirt: NASA's Human Computers" exhibit; as well as reports for various grants, program proposals, fliers, and other information about WISE programming efforts over the decades.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by topic, event, or program name.
  - Career Fairs
    - High Tech Career Connections, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Math and Science Career Fair, 1982 (Box 2)
    - New Detroit Career Awareness Fair, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Willow Run Intermediate School, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Women's Career Fair, 1980-1983; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Conferences
    - Image and Professionalism, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Options and Opportunities in Industry, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Women in Science, Engineering and Mathematics Regional Conference: Creating an Academic Community, 1993 (Box 2)
  - ENGAGE (ENGineering for HumAnity and ServinG SociEty)
    (ENGAGE was a non-residential one-week program for high school students that involved participants meeting other students and touring sites to learn more about computers.)
    - Photographs, 2009
  - Exhibits
    - Hidden Figures bicentennial exhibit documentation, circa 2017-2018
  - FIRST LEGO League (FLL)
    (Includes material related to one of the University of Michigan's For Inspiration and Recognition of Science and Technology (FIRST) LEGO League Teams, the M Go Blue Bots.)
    - Journal entries, 2005
    - Orientation presentation, 2005
    - M Go Blue Bots Logo, 2006
    - Nanotechnology notes and related material, 2006
    - Photographs, 2006
    - Photographs and videos, 2007
    - Training presentations and related documentation, 2007
    - Photographs and video, circa 2008
  - Future Science, Future Engineering (FSFE) Camp
    - Video, 2004
      [Access to this material is restricted to the reading room of the Bentley Historical Library]
  - Girls in Science and Engineering (GISE) Camp
    (Includes material related to one or more of camp's activities or topics, including cardboard canoes, chemistry, computer science, engineering, gaming for girls, geodesic structures, human genetics, physics, and/or robotics.)
    - Photographs, 2005
    - Presentation, 2006
    - Photographs, 2006
    - Photographs, videos, and related material, 2007
    - Photographs and videos, 2008
    - Photographs, 2011
  - Graduate Experience Program (GEP), 1996 (Box 2)
  - Graduate student programming photographs, 2006
  - LS&A/Women In Science Program Internships in the Sciences for Undergraduate Women, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Medical Student Interface, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous programs and events
    - Photographs, 2004-2005
      (Includes digital photographs of the following programs and topics: M Go Blue Bots, Sally Ride Science Festival, Science Fair, Tech Day Breakfast, and WISE Residence Program (RP).)
    - Photographs, 2006
  - Pipeline Program, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Roundtable Discussions
    - Positive Options for Women Scientists, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Sally Ride Science Festival photographs and related material, 2005
  - Science Day on Campus
    - Program
      - 1983 (Box 2)
        (includes photographs)
      - 1984 (Box 2)
      - 1985 (Box 2)
      - 1986 (Box 2)
      - 1987 (Box 2)
    - Report to Shell Companies Foundation, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Science for Life Program, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Sloane Proposal -- Summer Math Program for Undergraduate Women, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Southeast Michigan Science Fair
    - Photographs, circa 2004
    - Photographs, 2005
    - Presentation, 2006
  - Summer Internship Program
    - 1984 (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
    - 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989 (Box 3)
    - Final Grant Report, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Proposal, 1982-1984 (Box 3)
    - "Summer Internships in the Sciences for High School Women: A Model Program at the University of Michigan,", 1985 (Box 3)
  - Summer Research Experience for Minority High School Women, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Summerscience for Girls
    - Grant Proposal, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Interim Report, July 1989 (Box 3)
    - Program, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Program (includes photos), 1990 (Box 3)
    - Program, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Tray Lunches
    - "Do You Really Need a Ph.D. to Get a Job in Mathematics or Science?,", 1985 (Box 3)
    - Dual Career Couples, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Highest Paying Careers in the Sciences, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Science Writing Careers, ca., 1989 (Box 3)
    - Women in Technology In England: An Affirmative Action Perspective, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Trevor Field, 2007
    (Trevor Field, founder of PlayPumps International, visited the campus in 2007. WISE was one of several institutions that sponsored his visit.)
    - Fliers and related material
    - Interview with Ted London
    - Photographs
  - Warner-Lambert Lecture Series
    - Flyers, 1981-1990 (Box 3)
    - Guidelines Memo, 1981-1990 (Box 3)
    - History/Proposal, 1974-1975; 1980-1983 (Box 3)
    - List of Lecturers
      - By Co-Sponsoring Department, 1991 (Box 3)
      - By Year, 1981-1989 (Box 3)
    - Nominations, 1981-1990 (Box 3)
    - Press Releases and Publicity (Box 3)
  - Workshops
    - Career Options: The Mathematics Degree, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Careers in Computer Science, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Careers in Science, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Careers in Technology, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Careers in the Health Sciences, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Public Health Careers, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Resume Writing, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Surviving and Thriving in Graduate and Professional School, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Training and Development, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Women and Science, 1980-1986; 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Women in Medicine, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Women in Medicine and Dentistry, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Women in Science, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Women in Technology, 1983 (Box 3)
- Research, 1983-1990
  WISE conducted a number of independent research efforts focusing on students at the University of Michigan, which are documented in the Research series (0.15 linear feet). The results of these studies and questionnaires help the researcher understand perceptions and attitudes toward science among students at the university and contextualize WISE's programming direction and goals.
  - Experiences of Math/Physics Majors, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Factors that Influence Women's Pursuit of Scientific Fields, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Survey of University of Michigan Seniors' Career Aspirations, Especially Toward Careers in Science: Academic and Non-Academic Determinants, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
- Girls and Science and Technology (GASAT) IV, 1985-1988
  The Girls and Science and Technology (GASAT) IV series (0.35 linear ft.) includes correspondence relating to the GASAT conference held in Ann Arbor as well as documentation on the fundraising efforts and strategies used to underwrite the conference.
  - Correspondence, 1985-1988; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Fundraising, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Michigan Sesquicentennial Handout, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Publicity, 1987 (Box 3)
- Women's History in Michigan Science and Engineering Oral History Project, 2007
  The Women's History in Michigan Science and Engineering Oral History Project series includes digital recordings and transcripts of University of Michigan alumnae.
  - Audio recordings
    - Ajzenberg-Selove, Fay, 2007
    - Buckley, Paulita, 2007
    - Carter, Barbara, 2007
    - Connable, Tenho, 2007
    - Frank, Margaret, 2007
    - Holter, Francis, 2007
    - Kelly, Marilee, 2007
    - Natvig, Anne, 2007
    - Patterson, Dorothy, 2007
    - Pilchard, Patricia, 2007
    - Shumway, Sally, 2007
    - Sloat, Barbara, 2007
  - Transcripts, 2007
- Archived Website
  - Archived Women in Science and Engineering homepage, 2010-[ongoing]
Related Material
Researchers may wish to consult the following collections also held at the Bentley Historical Library: Center for the Education of Women (University of Michigan) records and the Women's History in Michigan Science and Engineering (University of Michigan) Web Archives.